Good morning, today is February 18th, it's the 3rd of אדר. Adar.
My name is Dan Margulis, I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer while
he's in Israel. And today's דף יומי Daf Yomi is עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah דף לד. Daf Lamed-Dalid. We're going to pick up a
few lines in on לד עמוד א, Lamed-Dalid Amud Aleph, where it
says רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay? This is following up the discussion
of wine barrels and wine flasks and how they can be כשר
koshered or not and all sorts of things like that. So רבי
עקיבא איקלע לגינזק, Rabbi Akiva ikla l'Ginzak, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva visited,
he went to גינזק. Ginzak. בעו מיניה, Ba'u minei, they asked him
questions, three questions, and it's going to turn out that for all
these three questions רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't know the answer, so
he had to then go ask some some help. So the first
question is מתנין לשעות או אין מתנין לשעות? matnin l'shaot o ein
mitanin l'shaot? Can you fast for hours? The way רש"י Rashi at
least understands this is the notion that if you were, if you
had not eaten anything sort of incidentally by and then it comes
around partway through the day and then you decide you want it
to be a fast day, does that count? There's also other ways
you could understand it, it could be like that they started a
fast day and then it rained in the afternoon and then you
know you discontinue the fast or not once the rains fall, questions
like that as well.
But they asked him do you fast for לשעות, shaot, that is
it doesn't have to be a full day, or אין מתנין לשעות,
ein mitanin l'shaot, or it has to be full days. לא הוה
בידיה, Lo hava b'yadei, and he didn't, he was not holding that
that answer. That is to have been able to teach them the
הלכה, Halacha, it wouldn't just be enough for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
to answer off the top of his head, but he would have
to have to hold the material, as if. I love that image
because nowadays very often you hear people say like, "Are you holding?"
Okay. אין לשא Ein l'sha so that was the first question. קנקנים
של עובדי כוכבים אסורים או מותרים? Kankanin shel ovdei kochavim asurim o
mutarim? They asked him are the the wine jars owned by idolaters,
are they אסורים, asurim, are they prohibited, or they מותרים? mutarim? Presumably
here not that whether right now are they permitted or prohibited, but
whether or not they could be כשר, koshered, they could be made
to be permissible later. Okay. לא הוה בידיה, Lo hava b'yadei, and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't know the answer to that either. במה
שמש משה כל שבעת ימי המילואים? Bameh shimmesh Moshe kol shivat yemei
hamiluim? And a question exactly related to our פרשה parashah this week,
פרשת תצוה: Parashat Tetzaveh: what did משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu wear during
the seven days of the מילואים, miluim, while אהרן Aharon and his
sons were being inaugurated to the כהנים, Kohanim, משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu
was the one who served as the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, because
the other five of them had to as if be joining into
the כהונה. Kehunah. So what did משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu wear during
the מילואים? miluim? לא הוה בידיה, Lo hava b'yadei, and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva didn't have a good answer to that either. So it's
very interesting here that there's a
אורח חיים Orach Chaim question, there's a יורה דעה Yoreh Deah question,
and then there's a בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash historical question that seemingly
doesn't have so much practical relevance. So the point is רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva didn't know the answer to any of these three questions.
אתא שאל בי מדרשא, Ata sha'al b'veit midrasha, then he went to
the בית מדרש Beit Midrash and he asked sort of the the
people who were gathered there in the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. אמרי
הלכתא, Amrei Hilkheta,
they told him the הלכה Halacha is מתנין לשעות, mitanin l'shaot, you
could fast for hours, and again the way רש"י Rashi understands לשעות,
l'shaot, that is that you accept the fast upon yourself in the
afternoon in the case where you had incidentally not eaten anything during
the morning, that it would count the whole day. ואם השלים, Ve'im
hishlim, what?
Don't we hold that if you you have to accept the fast
the day before?
I think usually you would have to accept the fast the day
before, that's exactly the question. I actually, as far as it is
for some reason I feel more inclined to read it not like
רש"י, Rashi, to understand it more like in the context of the
משניות Mishnayot in תענית Ta'anit that talk about that when it would
rain in the afternoon of a fast day, that מתנין לשעות mitanin
l'shaot means you can fast only the beginning of the day, that
is, you were fasting so that it would rain and then it
rains, are you allowed to discontinue the fast as soon as the
rain falls? I think that somehow it seems to me, רש"י's Rashi
reading it a different way, and obviously I have so much respect
and appreciation and love for רש"י, Rashi, but somehow for some reason
I don't know it's not clicking for me, because of here, ואם
השלים, ve'im hishlim, and if you did finish it, like השלים hishlim
sounds like the thing you would be discontinuing is at the end
of the fast, right? I could either מתנה לשעות, mitaneh l'shaot, fast
for only part of the day, or I could complete the fast.
So it sounds like the question is whether you would end the
fast early, not whether you would start it late. But anyway, מתנין
לשעות ואם השלים יתפלל תפילת תענית, mitanin l'shaot ve'im hishlim yitpallel tefillat
ta'anit,
and if you did complete the fast, then you should pray the
prayer of the fast day, that is regarding at least in Tannaitic
times the inclusion of the extra six extra ברכות brachot or five
extra ברכות brachot into the עמידה. Amidah.
Now we have the עננו Aneinu paragraph, which sort of takes the
place of that, but that's sort of... the designated prayer for the
fast day
because you count it as a real fast. But if you were
not משלים, mashlim, if you didn't complete the fast successfully, then you
would not say the special prayer for the fast, and that's basically
the הלכה halacha nowadays, which is that if you if you're fast
if you're not fasting on a fast day, then you you usually
do not add the additional prayers for the fast. The interesting question
becomes, what about what about יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and particularly what
about the מנחה Mincha of יום כיפור Yom Kippur Torah reading? Because
the שחרית Shacharit of יום כיפור Yom Kippur Torah reading is not
a fast day Torah reading. The שחרית Shacharit יום כיפור Yom Kippur
Torah reading is a יום טוב Yom Tov Torah reading as if
it's about the קדושת היום kedushat hayom of יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So I think more or less consensus opinion that is even someone
who's not fasting on יום כיפור Yom Kippur could have an עליה
aliyah at שחרית. Shacharit. Question is what about מנחה? Mincha? Is the
Torah reading we do at מנחה Mincha on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
like a fast day מנחה, Mincha, because we read Torah at fast
days at מנחה, Mincha, or is it like
a שבת מנחה Shabbat Mincha Torah
reading in the
nature there's just the aspect of שבת? Shabbat? None on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. What? None on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
יום כיפור Yom Kippur we read Torah.
You finish... you read Torah, but not the same...
it's not the same Torah, but meaning is the מהות, mahut, is
the nature of that Torah reading like quote unquote a fast day
Torah reading or is it like a שבת מנחה Shabbat Mincha Torah
reading in the nature there's just the aspect of שבת?
Shabbat? In the nature of if it was a fast day מנחה
Mincha Torah reading, then we would be doing a מנחה Mincha the
same
fast—no, maybe not, it's a different kind of fast day. Whatever. The
question is basically would you have to be fasting to have an
עליה aliyah at מנחה Mincha or not, and also do you mention
יום כיפור Yom Kippur in the ברכות brachot of the הפטרה Haftarah
at מנחה Mincha on יום כיפור Yom Kippur or not? And that's
מחלוקת machloket between the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and the רמ"א. Rema.
It's מחלוקת. machloket. There's a רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger about
it. Anyway, so it's an interesting question. Okay, so that's the first
first answer that they gave him, which is מתענים לשעות. mitanim l'sha'ot.
You could fast partial fast. To me it sounds like it means
discontinue the fast. For רש"י Rashi it sounds like it means picking
up the fast a few hours in. והלכתא קנקנים של עובדי כוכבים
לאחר י"ב חודש מותרים. V'hilchta kankanin shel ovdei kochavim l'achar yod bet
chodesh mutarin. And the law is that the jars, wine jars owned
by idolatrous peoples, that after 12 months of being unused are מותרים.
mutarim. Unless you don't want to do the whole water rinsing thing.
Because you could have just done that for three days.
Right. You could have done the water rinsing thing to leach out
the wine. Here this is saying if you just leave it dry
for 12 months, then then the pottery, whatever taste was absorbed into
the pottery is going to be inconsequential. And this again has all
sorts of interesting halachic implications, in particular there's a discussion, I think
it's in יורה דעה סימן קכ"א קכ"ב, Yoreh Deah siman kuf-kaf-alef kuf-kaf-bet,
where there's a discussion in the long piece in the פתחי תשובה
Pitchei Teshuvah about basically the question is what about porcelain dishes and
things like that? Certain kinds of ceramic dishes. Usually we say ceramic
and earthenware and porcelain can't be כשר kashered in any way. But
there are at least some opinions that say that after 12 months
it's possible to כשר kasher them because even whatever taste was there
that would have lingered after one day—right, after one day we say
whatever taste is absorbed, taste bad. And so it's of less consequence
הלכתית, halachit, but maybe after 12 months there really isn't any taste
left absorbed into the pot at all, sort of being derived from
these these מקורות mekorot about wine. In particular, you could make a
distinction—Wait, you're not saying the
taste goes anywhere?
Well, but the taste could degrade. It could be it's exposed to
the air, it's exposed to oxygen, it's exposed to sunlight. It could
totally, you know, degrade and disappear. Right?
Is that how taste works? Exposed to sunlight?
I don't know. It depends on what kind of a taste we're
talking about and how absorbed it is into the material and all
sorts of things.
Certainly, you know, מנהג minhag says, like for instance, do people say
that? Like let's say in your own stuff, like let's say you
טריף treif up a pot. Yeah. I want to כשר kasher it,
let it lie for 12 months.
Right. So no, because usually right, the only circumstances where it would
be is something that has no potential to be otherwise כשר. kashered.
So we're really speaking specifically about earthenware and things.
Yeah, but these קנקנים kankanin have a way of otherwise being כשר.
kashered. You could have just done the rinsing of the water.
Okay, but so that's part of the question.
Okay, so that's a real question.
But I don't know, off the top of my head I would
say generally if there's an accept—right, even by even the question for
for porcelain and earthenware and things for 12 months is a somewhat
controversial position. It's certainly not, you know,
accepted להלכה l'halacha by by many many פוסקים. poskim. So the it
sort of is at least something interesting to talk about. I don't
think certainly for something like a metal spoon where where the כשר
kashering is to put it in boiling water very easily, it's not
going to be such a recommendation that comes up. My sense would
be we wouldn't we wouldn't rely on something that's that's iffy if
there's there's an easier and better solution that's available. So here again
I you know the
question—maybe there wasn't an easier and better solution.
Okay, but maybe
because the whole thing was cold so they're relying on more קולות
kulot
than you'd have to do. Right, it's cold and it's because it's
דרבנן d'rabanan anyway. Like there are many layers of reason why you
could be more מקיל meikel by by these sorts of cases. Okay,
and then the question, the third question, במה שימש משה שבעת ימי
המילואים? Bameh shimish Moshe shivat yemei hamiluim? What did Moshe wear during
the seven days of the מילואים? miluim? בחלוק לבן. B'chaluk lavan. He
wore a white... a white smock, a white shirt, but not exactly
like any of the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna necessarily so as to
distinguish between משה רבנו Moshe Rabbeinu and אהרן Aharon and אהרן's Aharon
four sons. רב כהנא מתני בחלוק לבן שאין בו אמרא. Rav Kahana
matnei bechaluk lavan she'ein bo imra. And רב כהנא Rav Kahana later
clarified, that is after the period of the תנאים Tannaim into the
period of אמוראים, Amoraim, that it was a white shirt, a white
smock that did not even have a hem. The hem was not
an embroidered hem with any of the fine materials of the בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehuna so as to people shouldn't confuse the clothing that
משה Moshe was wearing from that which אהרן Aharon and the other
כהנים kohanim were wearing. Okay.
So that concludes this discussion, at least a bit. We're going to
have a bit more about the significance of twelve months. So let's
see here now. תנו רבנן החרצנים והזגים של עובדי כוכבים. Tanu rabbanan
hachartzanim vehazagim shel ovdei kochavim. The grape seeds and grape stems. Sounds
like נזירות. Nezirus. It sounds like נזירות Nezirus as well. Obviously there's
so much overlap when we're talking about wine. We have so many
different realms of הלכה halacha which discuss wine in its different applications.
So the ברייתא Baraita says, תנו רבנן החרצנים והזגים של עובדי כוכבים,
Tanu rabbanan hachartzanim vehazagim shel ovdei kochavim, the grape seeds and grape
stems that are owned by idolaters. לחים אסורים. Lachim assurim. If they're
still moist, if they're still wet, they're considered prohibited because whatever residual
juice or residual wine has absorbed into the...
You said grape stems, I always thought it was seeds and skins.
Seeds and skins, stems, they're little...
You can eat the skin, you can't eat the stem.
That's true. It may, if I'm remembering correctly,
seeds and peels. Seeds and peels. Okay, I'll take back. Not the
stems, the peels, the skins. Okay. So לחים אסורים, lachim assurim, while
they're wet, while they still have juice or still have wine absorbed
into the seeds and the skins, then they're prohibited because whatever amount
of wine would be on them is considered סתם יינם. stam yeinam.
יבשים מותרים. Yeveshim mutarim. And if they've dried out, then they become
permissible. Okay. So היכי דמי לחים היכי דמי יבשים? Heichi dami lachim
heichi dami yeveshim? So which counts as wet and which counts as
dry? אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, so it's interesting, this ברייתא
Baraita was from period of תנאים, Tannaim, was left unspecified. And now
we have אמוראים Amoraim coming to clarify. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda quoted שמואל, Shmuel,
לחים כל י"ב חודש יבשים לאחר י"ב חודש. lachim kol yud-bet chodesh
yeveshim le'achar yud-bet chodesh. So the first twelve months is considered to
be moist. Takes a year for the grape skins to dry out.
It's very interesting, you imagine... Wait, what are you worried about exactly?
I mean...
We're worried that if that סתם יינם stam yeinam and יין נסך
yayin nesech are אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Right? So if the skins
and seeds are considered to have absorbed liquid of סתם יינם, stam
yeinam, then they themselves will be אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah because there's
a residual liquid.
But the way you get the liquid out is by squeezing them.
Okay. Right?
But you can't squeeze every little drop, right? Right. There's, it's still,
if it's still moist...
But what happens is like the leftover stuff.
This is the leftover stuff.
No, I mean, like you squeeze it and any of that wine
then they libated it to their עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. They're not
using this stuff.
No, but there's still juice and wine residual in the grapes. It's
not about necessarily the potential for them to use it for עבודה
זרה avodah zarah at this point. Right? It's we've defined wine is
a problem and this has moisture in it, grape moisture, grape liquid
on the skins and the seeds and therefore it's going to be
a problem as long as they're moist.
Meaning because like we say in general, so we've abstracted this to
the point where...
It's abstracted. Well, again, the דרבנן d'rabbanan of סתם יינם stam yeinam
is not necessarily about the potential to be used for עבודה זרה
avodah zarah and so it could be any amount, any even minuscule
amount of this סתם יינם stam yeinam is going to be a
problem.
So now we're just putting things in הלכה halacha category. Meaning like
you know, because logically I don't see like, you know, if we're
really worried about...
Well, I'll put it to you this way, right? Like you squeeze
your grapes and you get wine out. If I squeezed a little
bit harder, I could get a little bit more wine out. So
at what point is it considered squeezed out enough or dry enough?
Like all of these things need to have a legal definition in
order for the הלכה halacha to be able to categorize and quantify.
So here at least, and again, it sounds, I mean again, but
twelve months sounds like a long time for something to dry out.
But if you think about it, when you're at a winery or
something like that... Well, you could reconstitute it. Well, first of all,
you could reconstitute it, you could soak them with water and things
like that. But also when they dump out all the skins and
the seeds and everything, they dump it in a big pile, like
on the trash pile. So it's going to stay moist for a
long time because it's all clumped together. So it's not going to
dry out so quickly necessarily. Okay. So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, לחים כל י"ב חודש. lachim kol yud-bet
chodesh. They're considered to be moist for twelve months. And יבשים לאחר
י"ב חודש. yeveshim le'achar yud-bet chodesh. And then they're after that they're
considered to be dry after twelve months. You could make all sorts
of comparisons to the mourning period that somehow twelve months is amount
of time also it takes sort of to reach a new stage
of an emotional connection as well. That is something is drying up,
something is creating more separation there. I don't know, you could make
some kind of...
So one year because if it's an עיבור Ibur year?
The הלכה Halakha says 12 months and similar to questions of קדיש
Kaddish and אבלות Avelus and things like that, when we say 12
months, do we mean a calendar year, do we mean 12 months,
12 months, and if it's a leap year then it will end
a month early and things like that? And that's often causes some
complications around יארצייט Yahrtzeit and things for the month of אדר. Adar.
As far as I would understand it, 12 months to me sounds
like 12 months.
But again, sometimes 12 months is a year. I don't know. Yeah.
Can I just clarify סתם יינם stam yaynam is that wine of
idol worship?
Wine owned by, touched by, handled by
non-Jews,
not even just idol worship.
And יין נסך Yayin Nesech would be?
יין נסך Yayin Nesech is wine which has really been used for
libations. The thing is and the complication is that throughout our מסכת
Masechet and certainly throughout the works of the ראשונים, Rishonim, the terms
are conflated and the term יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, יין נסך Yayin
Nesech is used even to refer to wine which is only prohibited
מדרבנן miderabbanan because of a problem of סתם יינם. stam yaynam. So
the precision of the terminology is important to consider. Are we talking
about a דאורייתא Deoraisa or a דרבנן? Derabbanan? Are we talking about
a problem of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Are we talking about a
more general sort of כשרות kashrus problem? But at the end of
the day, when you read halachic sources, when you read the גמרות
Gemaras and things, it sometimes can be very challenging to parse what's
actually being discussed because there's so much overlap. Because there's so much
commonality, right? The whole דרבנן גזירה derabbanan gezeirah of סתם יינם stam
yaynam is treat this as if it is יין נסך. Yayin Nesech.
So that's part of the complication.
Yeah, well then it's like treating everything else because it might have
been like this and
it might have been that. Okay, we're going to get into some
of that too. Okay. So איתמר. Itmar. אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbah bar bar Channah amar Rabbi Yochanan. So
רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Channah quotes from רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. We have this מימרא: memra: כשהן אסורין אסורין אפילו בהנאה.
Keshen asurin asurin afilu behanaah. When they are prohibited, that is presumably
referring to the grape skins and grape seeds, they remain prohibited even
prohibited בהנאה, behanaah, that is because they're wet, they're wet with what's
halachically considered wine. So if the wine is אסור בהנאה, assur behanaah,
then the grape skins and grape seeds are also אסור בהנאה. assur
behanaah. כשהן מותרין Keshen mutarin and when they become permitted, מותרין אפילו
באכילה, mutarin afilu beachilah, and when they become permissible after 12 months,
they are permitted even to be eaten. So that's very interesting. This
should have very important implications, I would say, for let's say raisins,
כשרות kashrus of raisins and things like that because if there's a
problem a non-Jewish person is pressing the grapes or whatever and they
squeeze the juice and process them for raisins, it could be a
problem of סתם יינם. stam yaynam. If you let them dry out
for 12 months, it's not going to be a problem. So that's
a very interesting suggestion. What?
What would we say about that?
I would say that that would be a great way to make
raisins. As far as I understand to make raisins, they don't even
squeeze the grapes at all anyway. There's no juice. Yeah, that's what
I was going to say. But maybe you're concerned about the juice
dripping? I don't know the realities of do
raisins need an השגחה hashgacha then?
I would think it's probably better to get raisins with a השגחה.
hashgacha. I know, for example, the Sun-Maid raisins are under Triangle K,
and Triangle K generally at least in our communities is somewhat of
a more questionable הכשר hechsher at least for certain things. As far
as I know, lots and lots of people eat Sun-Maid raisins. So
it's an interesting thing of like, okay, you know, what are the
קולות kulas or what, you know, why is it that Sun-Maid had
a deal with Triangle K and not the OU or anything else?
I don't know. These are all questions for people who know how
you know industrial כשרות kashrus works. I don't know. I was just
asking הלכה. halacha. The הלכה halacha as far as I understand, if
you take a if someone takes a grape off the tree and
puts it to dry, there's no halachic problem. But the problem is
if they squeeze a little bit and a little bit of juice
comes out and then
but they're not trying to squeeze it here.
So these are all big questions. I know and I forget it
was הרב טולידאנו Rabbi Toledano has a book like Fountain of Fountains
of Light or something like this. One of these English הלכה halacha
books that was written. He was a British rabbi.
And there he basically makes argument that modern industrial produced grape juice
should all be כשר kosher because all of the crushing and pressing
and squeezing and everything is done by machine. And then it goes
into a then it's pasteurized and then it goes into a bottle
and then the bottle is closed. It's on some huge industrial assembly
line. And there's no no person is there squeezing the juice and
touching the juice while it's throughout. It's all automated. So that's certainly
an interesting argument. As far as I you know, I don't know
the details of of the specifics how the plants are set up
and everything to be able to say whether I I think that's
something you could rely on halachically or not. But it's at least
in theory it would be good.
Someone might ask you this one day.
Someone already asked me this and I said I don't know the
answer. I'm going to take a trip to go visit the Welch's
grape juice or whatever, I don't know. Okay. כשהן אסורין אסורין אפילו
כשהן מותרין מותרין אפילו בהנאה. Keshen asurin asurin afilu keshen mutarin mutarin
afilu behanaah. Third to last line on ל"ד ע"ב. Lamed Daled Amud
Of. אמר רב
זביד.
Amar Rav
Zevid. האי דרדייא דחמרא דארמאי. Hai dardaaya dechamra dearmaye. בתר תריסר ירחי
שתא שרי. batyar treisar yarchy shata sharei.
After 12... months, then they become permissible.
We had this already, didn't we? דקנקנין דעובדי כוכבים הרי בשנים עשר
חודש מותרין. dekankanin de'ovdei chochavim harei bishneim asar chodesh mutarin.
Yeah, so maybe he's making a specific, even you might have thought
that these ones made of a different material, they're made of a
different kind of pottery or something like that, if it's more inferior
pottery it's more absorbent, I don't know, maybe that would be a
reason why you would have thought they should be...
Extensive note here about...
Extensive note here. There's an extensive the תוספות Tosafot here. Yeah, I
don't want to get into it.
Right, you're talking about whether this
was first soaked in water to make an inferior wine known as
תמד temed and then that plus the... Oh, he's saying this is
sediment. This is sediment, not the jugs is what he...
Oh, the דורדייא dordaya is the sediment. Okay. Right. Is that right?
One second.
שמרים. shmarim. Oh, where's רש"י? Rashi?
Yeah, רש"י Rashi said they're שמרים. shmarim. So it's like a yeast,
it's like the sediment from the bottom of the wine barrel that
contains the yeast. Ah, so I understand. So they're saying if you
let it dry out for 12 months, then whatever wine was in
it has evaporated and now what you're left with is just a
dry yeast material or whatever.
Before we were asking about the jugs and the...
No, so this is about seeds and peels and now we're talking
about sediment from the actual comes from the wine production.
There's a lot of detail here about that part.
Right, right. So that's I didn't want to get so into it
because exactly it gets a little bit technical. Okay. אמר רב חביבא
בריה דרבא: Amar Rav Chaviva brei deRava: הני גולפי? hani gulfi?
What about the גולפי? gulfi? גולפי gulfi are the are different kind
of jugs, right?
Jugs. Yeah, different kind of jugs. הני גולפי בתר תריסר ירחי שתא
שרי. hani gulfi batar treisar yarchi shata sharei. After 12 months they're
also going to be permissible to use. אמר רב חביבא Amar Rav
Chaviva and רב חביבא Rav Chaviva further said: הני אבותא דטייעי, hani
avata detayei,
the... Yeah, they've translated as canteens. Canteens, wine skins. רש"י Rashi says:
חמת מאור עב. chemet me'or av. It's made from a thick leather.
קורין אותו בוטין. korin oto butin.
And טייעי tayei are those travelers, travelers who travel in the desert
and things, people often bring drinks in a bag, in the skins,
right? There's one of the קינות kinot for תשעה באב Tisha B'Av
is about how when we were exiled in the... no, the קופים,
kufim, right? The first... the first exile, the people from what from
Arabia or whatever gave us wine wine skins to drink, but they
were full of air and they breathed in the air and they
died.
First they gave them salty things.
Right, salty. Right, all of these kind of things. Right, exactly.
Okay. אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא: Amar Rav Acha brei deRav
Ika: הני פורצני דארמאי בתר תריסר ירחי שתא שרי. hani purtzanei de'armai
batar treisar yarchi shata sharei.
And these other certain kind of jars, פסולת של אבנים psolet shel
avanim or it's the pits or the seeds, right? Basically,
these are all the clarifications that basically all of these different things,
if the concern is that it was wet with wine, then if
you let it dry out for 12 months, it's not a problem.
That's overarching thing and each of these different rabbis were talking about
a slightly different case and slightly different details and they're basically reinforcing
the same
פסק. psak. אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא Amar Rav Acha brei deRava
and רב אחא Rav Acha the son of רבא Rava said: הני
גולפי שחימי ואוכמי, hani gulfi dechimei ve'uchmei,
the black and brown pottery type jars, בתר תריסר ירחי שתא שרי.
batar treisar yarchi shata sharei. After 12 months they're also permissible. So
they're made of different pottery, they're made of they're different types of
refuse from the wine production. All of these different kind of things,
as long as they dry out for 12 months, they're permissible. Then
we continue with a discussion of מוריאס. muryas. So I
people who know me on Facebook can see what I posted here
a bit from Wikipedia and a bit from
there was an article in Biblical Archaeology Review. I'm just going to
read to you here. This is about Roman eating process which is
basically that they would take fish. So there's something Charlie would love
this, I know, sorry he's not here. The Romans produced something like
a fish sauce. People know about like Southeast Asian fish sauce and
things like this. So it was called garum and it was made
from fish that was soaked with salt in water for a long
time and and fermented. The fish that sinks to the bottom is
was called... I'm going to write
it... was called hallex, which probably might come from the word like
halos is like salt. But so that was the fish that sinks
to the bottom of the thing, which in Hebrew is going to
turn into חילק. chilek. Okay.
חילק. chilek. Okay.
And מוריאס muryas is then if they take the garum and dry
it out until it forms like crystals and a like a paste,
a thick paste. So that's מורייא muraya and מוריאס muryas in in,
you know, Hebrew. But there's a fascinating discussion here of
a graffiti that was found at the in Pompeii and there are
some archaeologists who suggest that there were inscriptions that said on some
of these jars garum castum, pure garum, and the suggestion is that
these were fish fish paste that was produced only from כשר kosher
*kosher* fish for the Jewish inhabitants of Pompeii.
Jewish inhabitants of Pompeii?
There's this is a major debate among the archaeologists I found out
whether or not there were Jews in Pompeii or not. So there's
at least this one archaeologist has this theory. You find anything like?
They found jars that say that that they it seems like they
were eating only specific מוריאס *murias* or only only specific garum.
Oh, it could be that you know like just like you go
to the restaurant and you want salmon, you want tuna, whatever. Right.
So I don't know. So it sounds like most of this garum
was produced from mackerel, which is a כשר *kosher* kind of fish,
but I would imagine if mackerel was difficult to get or they
would be finding other you know other kinds of fish would make
it so that you could save some money, you could switch in
other kinds of fish. So certainly our initial reaction to say, oh
it's some kind of a fish sauce produced whatever, the question could
be, oh is it a כשר *kosher* fish or not? Maybe the
problem is is כשרות Kashrut *kashrut* question. The problem is it's listed
in our משנה Mishnah *mishna* as a discussion of things which are
אסור asur בהנאה *assur behana'ah*. And I think even the משנה Mishnah
*mishna* says explicitly
part of the concern is that they would put wine into the
sauce. Is that correct?
It says here that מוריאס *murias* was never made with non-כשר *kosher*
fish.
That comes up in the גמרא Gemara *gemara* as well, but I'm
trying to say that it may not necessarily the archaeology may not
be true. They mixed with wine, right. I'm trying to find it
in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, though I thought it was in the
משנה Mishnah *mishna*. המוריאס וגבינת בית אוניא וקני
של עובדי כוכבים אסורין ואיסורן איסור
הנאה *Hamuryas vegivinat beis unya veknei shel ovdei kochavim asurin veisuran isur
hana'ah*.
It doesn't say explicitly in the משנה Mishnah *mishna* that they are
made with wine, but that would that would be the only reasonable
reason why they would be prohibited אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah*. We're going
to see our משנה Mishnah, *mishna* is going to be contrasted with
the following משניות *mishnayot* deal with things which are prohibited to eat
but are not אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah*, and those are either כשרות
Kashrut. *kashrut* questions or those are questions of other איסורי דרבנן *issurei
derabbanan* about foods produced by non-Jews. So we'll see here the מוריאס
*murias* question. So תנו רבנן מוריאס *Tanu Rabbanan murias*, מוריאס אומן מותר
*murias uman mutar*. So the ברייתא *braisa* says that מוריאס *murias* produced
by a craftsman, by a professional מוריאס *murias* maker is permissible because
as David was saying there is a presumption that they don't adulterate
it with non-כשר *kosher* fish or with wine. That is, if it's
made professionally it's just made with fish and salt and water and
it's no problem.
In
the first stages.
In the first stages.
I'm sorry, wait. There's two stages. You're going to a Jewish fishmonger
here?
No, you're going to any old fishmonger. They would actually import it.
They're going to see there's a discussion of transporting it by ship.
So it'd be produced in one place and then maybe transported in...
But I thought but I thought they'd use wine in it or
they don't?
You're saying we don't? No, they would add wine later or in
some later stage of the production they would add wine, but at
least the initial stage is produced only using fish would not be
a problem.
I would I would imagine that the any, so if you go
to a household they would use wine, I'd imagine wine is more
expensive. Why would they want to?
So the we're going to see the discussion of the price is
going to be important. In different locales it comes up right in
just a few lines. In some places the fish is more expensive
than the wine, so they would use wine to water it down
to save money, and in other places wine is more expensive than
fish and then they would keep it the wine out of the
fish, right?
So it's making a distinction between professional working and and and a
household. Right. That's the point, you can't trust the household. No.
We're going to see the household one.
Anyway, professional in the first stages is not going to use wine.
Right. They would make it three different... And the other thing which
I put on Facebook is that it actually there are different tiers
of quality. There would be the first pressing, which was for the
rich people and then lower on. It's like the version... extra virgin
olive oil. So they would take the same fish and ferment it
again with more water, the flavor would be weaker, so maybe they'll
have to add wine in order to adulterate it or to to
beef up the flavor in a case where there's less fish.
Where did you put this on Facebook?
I just posted on my on my post on דף יומי *Daf
Yomi*. Yeah, I it's like to put the דף יומי *Daf Yomi*
post. I put hashtag דף יומי *Daf Yomi*. People should there you
go. I'm not on Facebook. There also, so there you go, you
can't find it. Okay. מותר *Mutar*. רבי יהודה בן גמליאל אומר *Rabbi
Yehuda ben Gamliel omer*. רבי יהודה בן גמליאל *Rabbi Yehuda ben Gamliel*.
רבי יהודה בן גמליאל *Rabbi Yehuda ben Gamliel* is as far as
I know is oh
now I'm going to make a mistake because there are so many
different גמליאלס *Gamliels* and there are so many different יהודות *Yehudas*.
I think he's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*'s brother,
but I'm not 100% sure.
And there are multiple רבן שמעון בן גמליאלס *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliels*.
Anyway, so רבי יהודה בן גמליאל אומר משום רבי חנינא בן גמליאל
*Rabbi Yehuda ben Gamliel omer mishum Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel*. He quoted
his brother or his grandfather or something: אף חילק chilek אומן מותר
*Af chilek uman mutar*. And חילק chilek *chilek* is the like I
said the fish left over at the bottom. Again, there's a similar
presumption that if it comes from a professional producer and there's this
assumption that they don't put wine in in the high quality stuff.
If you're buying from the high quality stuff it's not going to
have wine in it. Okay. תניא אבימי בריה דרבי אבהו *Tanya Avimi
brei deRabbi Abahu*. אבימי *Avimi* quoted the son of רבי אבהו *Rabbi
Abahu* said: מוריאס אומן מותר *Murias uman mutar*. The מוריאס *murias* produced
by a professional producer is permissible. הוא תני לה והוא אמר לה
*Hu tani lah vehu amar lah*. He had told... but he was
also the one who had said it originally פעם ראשון ושני מותר,
when he taught it he said the first two pressings of the
fish that it's permissible שלישי אסור, shlishi assur, the third batch is
prohibited. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? פעם ראשון ושני דנפיש
שומנייהו Pa'am rishon vesheni denafish shumnayhu because there's a lot of grease
in the first two
times, לא צריך למרמוייהו חמרא. lo tzarich lemarmeihu chamra. They don't have
to add wine into the production the first two pressings because there's
enough oil in the fish. מכאן ואילך רמו בהו חמרא. Mikan ve'eilach
remu behu chamra. Afterward from the third pressing, they would add wine
because the flavor would be weaker. And then they would give it
to much lower class people or it was would be much cheaper.
Okay.
ההוא ארבא דמוריסא דאתו לנמליא דעכו. Hahu arba demuryasa de'atu lenamlya de'Akko,
Yeah, which Rashi?
דחילק, dechilek, you
know where it says חילק של עובדי כוכבים אסור אותו מדגים קטנים
וניכר הרבה ביחד ואינה אסורה מפני שערבונה אולי עם הדגים טמאים.
chilek shel ovdei kochavim assur oto midaggim ktanim venikar harbeh beyachad ve'eina
assura mipnei
she'irvunah ulay im hadaggim tme'im. So it's like he's saying is that
it's a matter of having non-kosher fish in there as well.
Right. So it sounds but it sounds like at least from the
research that I did
the archaeological understanding from Roman cookbooks and things like that is that
the חילק chilek is the leftovers from the מוריס muryas production, so
if there we have some kind of a חזקה chazakah that they
don't put non-kosher fish into the מוריס, muryas, it's at least reasonable
to assume that they wouldn't normally put non-kosher fish into the חילק
either.
But I guess what's interesting about it is you might say, oh
after they've pressed out all the juice or whatever then they have
all this crumbly fermented fish stuff so then let's add in some
other fish to like increase the volume, cheaper fish or whatever. I
don't know. So he's at least you know these תנאים Tannaim are
saying that it's permissible even to buy the חילק because again the
assumption is that they wouldn't be non-kosher fish into it. I think
nowadays obviously you know many of these הלכות halachot are things which
are you'd have to go by what the normal assumptions presumptions of
production could be. So is this sort of saying like oh you
could buy tuna fish without a הכשר hechsher because everyone knows tuna
fish is tuna fish or whatever something like
that at least in a theoretical kind of a state or whatever.
I would say the stakes are even higher. It's like this huge
multinational company. Right exactly.
If they found out
they're to ruin their business entirely.
Oh we found out they're putting octopus in the tuna fish then
everybody's going to freak out right. Especially now people have allergies and
all sorts of things. Okay so ההוא ארבא דמוריסא Hahu arba demuryasa
דאתו לנמליא דעכו, de'atu lenamlya de'Akko. there was a boat carrying מוריסא
muryasa that docked in the port of Akko. So אותיבי רבי אבא
דמן עכו נטורי
בהדה.
otivi Rabbi Abba demin Akko
naturi behadah. So he went to like to
go investigate it basically. So אמר ליה רבא עד האידנא מן נטרה.
amar leh Rava ad ha'idna man natrah. So
Rava said until this point one second I lost my spot. So
because the problem will be basically do we know that this מוריס
muryas is the good kind of מוריס muryas or not on the
boat right? That's sort of the question okay. So the concern is
that where did it come from? If it came from a place
where like I was saying before if wine is cheaper then the
problem will be that they would use wine to water it down
to save money and if it comes from place where wine is
expensive then it wouldn't be a problem but what about if it
came from produced
by a professional or not that's
the point so presumably this is sort of in somehow in parallel
to the discussion of the professional or not this is even a
professional but produced somewhere else where maybe they have different prices for
the wine
that'll change the concern or maybe
this is all in a place that's not produced by
professional then what once it's not professional right or something like that
which could make it different right for sure. So אמר ליה רבא
עד האידנא מן נטרה. amar leh Rava ad ha'idna man natrah. אמר
ליה amar leh עד האידנא ניחוש לה משום דמערבי בה
חמרא ad ha'idna nichosh lah mishum demervei bah chamra until this point
that is sort of the concern we have is whether or not
they've included wine into it. קיסתא דמוריס בלומא, Kista demuryas beluma,
if a קיסתא kista of מוריס muryas counts one לומא, luma, one
coin, one zuz, and קיסתא דחמרא בד' לומי kista dechamra bedaled luma'ei
and wine is much more expensive the same volume of wine costs
four times as much they're not going to add wine to the
מוריס muryas to water it down. אמר ליה רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא,
Amar leh Rabbi Yirmeya leRabbi Zeira, Rabbi Yirmeya said to Rabbi Zeira
דילמא איידי דצור אתו דשבו חמרא. dilma eidi deTzor atu deshavo chamra.
Maybe it came from Tzor and they did add wine because in
Tzor the value of wine was less and the value of מוריס
muryas was more so they would adulterate it there and then they
would bring it to somewhere else where actually the prices are inverted.
So it has to do sort of the price differential between Tzor
Tyre and Akko. אמר ליה התם עקולי ופשורי איכא. Amar leh hatam
ikulei ufshurei ika.
But if that would be the case then that would be a
rare case because the water next to Tzor is bad sailing so
people
had Okay. So now we get into the next discussion which is
a discussion is the first discussion of cheese. Obviously we're going to
have a later a later cheese discussion about regular cheese, but our
משנה Mishnah. had discussed cheese that specifically was a עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah problem of cheese because the משנה had said that cheese that
comes this was the משנה on כ"ט עמוד ב Kaf Tet Amud
Bet and the משנה had said that גבינות Gevinot sorry one second
גבינת בית אונייקי Gevinat Beit Unaiki is also a problem. The cheese
that comes from בית אונייקי. Beit Unaiki. So we'll see what the
גמרא
right now but then later on you remember you should want to
ask רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua why is it a problem
and then you didn't get an answer. He doesn't get an answer.
That's the main cheese discussion, which is the discussion of the real
the normal כשר cheese questions. But this is just right now question
of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah question. גבינת בית אונייקי. Gevinat Beit Unaiki.
אמר רבי
שמעון בן לקיש Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
said מפני מה אסרו גבינת אונייקי. mipnei mah asuru Gevinat Unaiki. Why
did they say that this cheese from בית אונייקי Beit Unaiki is
prohibited? מפני שרוב עגלים של אותה עיר נשחטין לעבודת כוכבים. Mipnei she'rov
agalim shel otah ir nishchatin l'avodah kochavim. Most of the calves in
that town are slaughtered for עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Now let's pause
for a second. How do you make cheese in Talmudic time? You
need two things. You need
a
thing and you need the milk. What's the thing? So this if
this is a this is what we call עור קיבה. Or Keva.
עור קיבה Or Keva is the stomach or the rumen of the
cow.
And basically make it into a bag, you tie it up and
you put the milk inside and it turns into cheese because the
enzymes in the stomach the enzymes in the stomach lining of the
calf curdled the milk and turned it into cheese. So it's called
עור קיבה. Or Keva. The skin of the קיבה Keva because קיבה
Keva is actually the stomach contents. הזרוע הלחיים והקיבה. Hazro alecha ha'einayim
vehakeva.
So קיבה Keva
right but there maybe refers actually to the עור קיבה Or Keva
whatever. At least in Mishnaic terminology and at least with some consistency
at least in the cheese discussion there will be a distinction between
קיבה Keva and עור קיבה Or Keva because קיבה Keva is totally
inedible. It's just the sort of stomach partially digested milk from a
calf's stomach. Contains some of the enzymes you could use to make
the cheese. It's not edible. The עור קיבה Or Keva could be
a problem. What are the problems? Number one is if it's a
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah problem. If the cow was sacrificed for עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah so now the physical substance of the skin of
the of the stomach will be prohibited because of עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. So that's what we're talking about here. Later when we'll get
into the כשרות questions we're going to have questions about oh is
this a problem of בשר בחלב? Basar B'chalav? Is this a problem
of נבילה? Neveilah? What what's the issue here about the cheese production
or is there a problem of them doing something else to the
cheese? They put wine into the cheese, they put grease you know
lard onto the surface of the cheese or something like that. And
I would think that they put snake venom into the cheese.
I would think that if they שחטed shecht this thing לעבודה זרה
l'avodah zarah there wouldn't be anything for you to buy right? You
put it on
their עולה.
ola. I don't know maybe they they שחטed shecht it and they
put you know one piece of meat or one piece of whatever
maybe they don't do קרבן עולה Korban Olah like we do קרבן
עולה. Korban Olah. They take a certain part of the animal right?
I always love this from the Prometheus myth, the Greek mythology. Part
of what Prometheus in the myth teaches human beings how to do
is how to trick the gods with the sacrifices. That is what
do they put on the sacrifices? They take the skin and the
bones and some of the fats and things and sort of wrap
it up and put it on the altar so it looks like
they're burning the whole animal and they keep the meat for themselves.
Which is not so different than what we do because a קרבן
שלמים Korban Shelamim or קרבן חטאת Korban Chatat most of the meat
of the animal is going to be eaten by someone. With the
חטאת Chatat it's going to be eaten by כהנים. Kohanim. For the
שלמים Shelamim some is given to the כהנים Kohanim and some the
owners eat.
The difference is we're not trying to trick anyone.
We're not trying to trick anyone. That's how God told us to
do it that it's supposed to bring us together and bring us
into the temple and and collaborate on those things. But I think
it's just an interesting point that in their mythology they depict it
as oh it's how can we trick the gods? We're going to
give them all the bad stuff that you can't eat and we're
going to keep all the meat for ourselves which is like such
an you know it's an interesting anyway.
Prob also shows you that generally you'd offer the whole thing.
Right but but then at a certain point early on in the
Greek paganism they stopped doing that and they started tricking them right?
So it's all anyway fine. So the רוב rov majority majority of
the calves in this town will be slaughtered for עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. Okay. מאי איריא רוב עגלים? Mai irya rov agalim? Is it
only a problem because the majority? אפילו מיעוט נמי. Afillu miyut nami.
Even if it's a מיעוט. miyut.
Why because of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah we're חושש choshesh for the
מיעוט? miyut?
Seemingly. Seemingly we'll be even concerned about a minority. So here it's
different because like for כשרות. But one second דהא רבי מאיר חייש
למיעוטא De'ha Rabbi Meir chayish l'miyuta because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
the one who right the question of the author of our משנה
but רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is the one who who is concerned
even in cases of a מיעוט. miyut. Very fascinating. I think this
is related. I think it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who in חולין
Chulin discusses the possibility of, right, there's a, if there's a hole
in
the lungs, right?
Not in the lungs, in the... I'm going to mix up which
one is which.
It's in the esophagus. If there's a puncture hole
נקוה הושט, nikva ha-veshet, so it's in the esophagus. If there's a
puncture hole in the esophagus of the animal, then it's a טריפה
treifa and the whole animal is a טריפה. treifa. So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is the one who always says שמא במקום נקב שחט,
shema bemakom nekev shachat, that maybe when you did the שחיטה shechita
the knife blade slaughtered the animal exactly over the spot where there
was already a puncture, so you can't check it because you destroyed
the puncture in the act of שחיטה. shechita. Ah, so maybe רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir was a vegetarian because he was חושש למיעוטא. choshesh
le-miuta. That's an interesting speculation. Anyway, okay.
דהא רבי מאיר חייש למיעוטא. deha Rabbi Meir chayish le-miuta. אי אמרת
רוב איכא מיעוטא. ei amrat rov ika miuta. So if you say
go by the majority, then there'll be a problem of minority. אלא
אי אמרת מיעוט כיון דאיכא רוב עגלים דאינש שחטי לעבודה כוכבים, ela
ei amrat miut keivan de-ika rov agalim de-inish shachti le-avodah kochavim, but
if you say it's a problem for the minority,
since there is a majority of calves that people slaughter for עבודה
כוכבים, avodah kochavim, right? If you say the majority of the calves
are slaughtered for עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, it's one thing. Fine, so
it's a majority. If it's a minority, then wait a second, then
you have actually a double רוב rov because what happened? You have
רוב rov of the calves are not slaughtered for עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah ואיכא נמי שאר בהמות דאינש שחטי לעבודה כוכבים ve-ika nami shear
behemot de-inish shachti le-avodah kochavim and all of the other animals are
also even more a majority. That is, what do you have? There's
so many different things on the board.
You have like a Venn diagram of these are all the בהמות,
behemot, okay, and then you could have עגלים, agalim, right?
And then you have some section of the עגלים agalim are for
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So then it's a double minority. That would
be the point and a double minority what are we going to
say? אלא אי אמרת מיעוט כיון דאיכא רוב עגלים דאינש שחטי לעבודה
כוכבים ואיכא נמי שאר בהמות, ela ei amrat miut keivan de-ika rov
agalim de-inish shachti le-avodah kochavim ve-ika nami shear behemot, so there's also
all of the other animals דאינש שחטי לעבודה כוכבים de-inish shachti le-avodah
kochavim are not slaughtered for עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. הוה ליה מיעוטא
דמיעוטא. hava lei miuta de-miuta. It's a minority of the minority. So
when you have a double minority, even those who are concerned about
a minority normally, just a regular מיעוט, miut, are not concerned for
a double minority. מיעוטא דמיעוטא לא חייש רבי מאיר. miuta de-miuta lo
chayish Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is not concerned that the
ones that are slaughtered for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah are a minority
of the calves and the calves are minority of all of the
animals. So therefore it must be that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir thinks
actually in this town, and maybe that's why it was specifically only
one town out of everywhere, there was this concern because it's the
actual majority of all of the calves are slaughtered for עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah and therefore it will be a minority of בהמות behemot
but it will be the majority of the עגלים agalim and that's
why it's a single מיעוט. miut. אמר ליה רבי שמעון בר אליקים
לרבי שמעון בן לקיש. amar lei Rabbi Shimon bar Elyakim le-Rabbi Shimon
ben Lakish. So רבי שמעון בר אליקים Rabbi Shimon bar Elyakim told
ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, כי נשחטין לעבודה כוכבים מאי הוי? ki nishchatin
le-avodah kochavim mai havei? If they are slaughtered for עבודה כוכבים, avodah
kochavim, so what's the point? והא איהו שרי? ve-ha ihu sharei? Like
shouldn't it still be that you, ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, will say
that it's not a problem? Why? דאתמר, de-itmar, you say, השוחט את
הבהמה לזרוק דמה לעבודה כוכבים והקטיר חלבה לעבודה כוכבים. ha-shochet et ha-beheimah
lizrok damah le-avodah kochavim ve-hiktir chalavah le-avodah kochavim. So if a person
who slaughters an animal in order to take the blood and sprinkle
it for the purpose of an idolatrous sacrifice or to burn its
חלבים, chalavim, its the fats,
for idolatrous sacrifice, רבי יוחנן אמר אסורה. Rabbi Yochanan amar asura. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says prohibited, the whole animal becomes prohibited. קסבר מחשבין
מעבודה לעבודה, kasavar machshivin me-avodah le-avodah, that the cognition, the planning, transfers
from one עבודה avodah to the other. That is, my plan was
to do the blood, but then what did I end up doing?
I ended up burning the fats. So I didn't do what I
originally planned to do, but I planned to do עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah and I ended up doing עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that is still problematic because you can transfer
the מחשבה, machshava, transfer the mind state from one עבודה avodah to
another, from one act of worship for the other. ואלפינן חוץ מפנים,
ve-alfinan chutz mi-pnim, and we can learn by implication the definitions of
what counts as an
עבודה avodah from פנים pnim to חוץ, chutz, from inside the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash to outside. That is, how do we define what
counts as עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? We define it based on what
counts as עבודה, avodah, service for sacrifices in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. So the זריקת הדם, zerikat ha-dam, sprinkling the blood, and the
הקטר חלבים, hekter chalavim, burning the fats on the altar and things
like that are both considered עבודות avodot in the Temple. Only a
כהן kohen could do them, things like that. And therefore we could
transfer, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says we apply this principle מחשבין
מעבודה לעבודה. machshivin me-avodah le-avodah. just like in the temple we also
have a principle that the mind state is going to transfer from
one עבודה avoda to another, even if you do something different than
what you originally planned, this is going to have major implications when
we learn זבחים Zevachim for how פיגול piggul works and things like
that.
Does it have anything to do with doing something different? I mean,
this is, meaning, no, it's just a step later. In other words,
I'm going to שחט shecht this animal now for,
but the שחיטה shechting has nothing to do with it. I'm thinking
okay, later when the blood comes out I'm going to use that
for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, that's what it means. In other words,
so is the problem that it becomes אסור now, the שחיטה, shechita,
because of what I want to do with it later? That's to
me what it sounds like.
Does it permeate? The mind state, right.
But the point is that the mind state now, the question is
whether the שחיטה shechita counts as an עבודה avoda or not. That's
what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is going to say. But it's not
that you change
your mind or do something later.
Fine, you don't have to change your mind, right, it's that whether
does the mind state now at the time of שחיטה, shechita, that
affects the whole animal, right? Because later I'm going to take the
חלבים chalavim and burn them on the מזבח mizbe'ach and the question
will be whether the קיבה keivah is going to still be permissible
or not. So will the קיבה keivah of the animal become prohibited
because of עבודה זרה avoda zara because you שחט shechted the animal
with the mental plan that I'm going to sacrifice part of the
animal for עבודה זרה avoda zara later? Right.
So that's מחשבין מעבודה לעבודה, machshivin me'avoda l'avoda, that your מחשבה, machshava,
your thought process, transfers from one עבודה avoda to another. And רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan will consider שחיטה shechita as one of the עבודות.
avodos. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, ריש לקיש אומר מותרת, Reish Lakish
omer muteres, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that the animal remains permissible.
Why? Because he disagrees about that assumption. That is ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, if you look at רש"י Rashi
explains, רש"י Rashi says, רבי יוחנן אמר אסורה, Rabbi Yochanan amar asurah,
because the point there, no, רש"י Rashi doesn't explicate it, but the
point is that
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish basically, it goes on, ריש לקיש לא ילפינן
מפנים, Reish Lakish lo yalfinan mipnim, right, that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
is not going to extrapolate the laws of עבודה זרה avoda zara
from the laws of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. What's interesting about
שחיטה, shechita, שחיטה shechita in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash actually, one
of unique among the עבודות, avodos, it's the only עבודה avoda that
a non-כהן kohein is permitted to do. There's a bit of a
question about how permissible or how recommended it would be for a
ישראל Yisrael to sacrifice their own animal, and then the כהן kohein
will do the קבלת הדם kabbalas hadam and the זריקת הדם zrikas
hadam and everything else, but it's sort of interesting question. Okay. אמר
ליה תרמנא שתך amar lei tarmnach shatach ובאומר בגמר זביחה הוא
עובדה. uv'omer bigmar zevichah hu uvda. So they basically responded to him,
that is ריש לקיש Reish Lakish responded to רבי שמעון בר אליקים
Rabbi Shimon bar Elyakim and said
תרמנא שתך, tarmnach shatach, you should have a ברכה, bracha, you should
have good luck.
ובאומר בגמר זביחה הוא עובדה, uv'omer bigmar zevichah hu uvda, so he
clarifies his point, which is that if you actually were thinking about
the שחיטה shechita itself for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, then the דאמר
בלבו, d'amar belibo, רש"י Rashi says, ואמר בלבו בזביחה זו עובדה לעבודת
כוכבים, ve'amar belibo b'zevichah zo oveid l'avodat kochavim, you're actually dedicating the
שחיטה shechita itself to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, that's going to be
a problem for the whole animal. ובהא דינא דמצד דזביחה הוי עבודה
חשובה כזריקה. uv'hai dina demitzad dezevichah havei avoda chashuva kezrikah. So ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish will consider the שחיטה shechita to be a significant
עבודה avoda such that if the שחיטה shechita was done with עבודה
זרה avoda zara in mind, then the animal will be prohibited. And
that's how ריש לקיש Reish Lakish could still hold by the משנה,
but can have a מחלוקת machlokes with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan about
this other case where suppose you slaughtered the animal without עבודה זרה
avoda zara in mind, but then you end up bringing it for
עבודה זרה avoda zara later, the animal won't be prohibited. Okay.
So I'm sorry, so this is like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir or
in other words
because it's still a מיעוט. miyut.
I'm not sure it has to do with, we had two different
points to clarify about our משנה. Number one is how can it
be that we would say that the cheeses of this city, בית
אונייקי, Beis Unaikai, are prohibited because of עבודה זרה? avoda zara? And
we said, oh, isn't it a minority because even if it's the
majority of the calves, it's a minority of the animals in total.
So we said oh it must be רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because
רבי מאיר חייש למיעוטא. Rabbi Meir chayish le'miyuta. So רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, but not a double מיעוט miyut and that's why it had
to be the majority of the calves and not the minority, which
explains why it's that one city specifically. The other thing we had
to ask
is the majority of the calves, the minority of the animals, but
you still חושש choshesh for, right.
The other question is how can we determine whether
the cow's stomach will have been made prohibited because of עבודה זרה
avoda zara even if it's being sold in the marketplace later? That
is, how can it be that even the parts that aren't actually
dedicated to עבודה זרה avoda zara are going to be a problem?
And that's this מחלוקת machlokes between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish about sort of how much does your מחשבה, machshava,
your intent, at the time of the שחיטה shechita transfer over or
at the time of for the future actions you're going to take
that are going to be עבודה זרה avodah zarah worship transfer back
to the moment of the שחיטה shechitah to dedicate the whole animal
to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it does,
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish basically is distinguishing between how explicit you made
your the act of שחיטה shechitah to be dedicated to עבודה זרה
avodah zarah or not. We have only one more minute, maybe we
should just stop here, we'll pick up here from tomorrow morning, and
I apologize about the lack of video. It seems we're logged out
of the video. I'll try to email with Rabbi Linzer today, hopefully
he's not too jet lagged to answer an email about the login.
It will make it so that we'll have video tomorrow. Hope everyone
has a great day.
You don't have to apologize to us, we're the ones who are
here today.
You're the ones who are here, but I'm apologizing to the audio
recorder as well. All right, bye-bye.